### **Mahendra Duwal Shrestha**

4831 E Summit Cir Apt 136 ● Knoxville, TN 37919 ● (865) 441-7363 ● <u>mduwalsh@vols.utk.edu</u> • <u>duwal.mahendra@gmail.com</u>

#### **SUMMARY**

A software engineer with 2.5 years of professional industry experience in C#, Asp.Net, Java, Grails. Proven abilities in analysis, test development and application development in both new and existing projects. 2.5 years of research experience in developing mathematical simulation programs involving cluster computations in C/C++.

### **OBJECTIVE**

A software engineering position where I can exploit my skills and experience, and further broaden my knowledge and skills.

# **EDUCATION**

MS in Computer Science, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, GPA: 3.9

Major courses taken: Computer Systems Organization, Software Systems, Algorithms, Introduction to Pattern Recognition, Databases and Scripting Languages, Applied Cryptography, Distributed System Algorithms

*Thesis*: Efficient Simulation Of A Simple Evolutionary System

# **BE** in Electronics and Communication Engineering, Pulchowk Engineering Campus, Tribhuvan University, Nepal, GPA: 3.8

2007-2011

### **SKILLS SUMMARY**

•	Programming Language:	C, C++, Java, C#, Groovy, Javascript, PHP, Perl, Python
•	Web Technologies:	HTML5, Groovy on Grails, ASP.Net, ASP.Net MVC, Ajax,
		Jquery, JSON, Web services, WCF services, REST, SOAP,
		Hibernate, Entity Framework, LINQ, NUnit, JUnit, Spock,
		Spring MVC
•	Version Control:	git, SVN
•	Databases:	MYSQL, MSSQL
•	Tools:	Gnuplot, pthreads, CUDA, OpenMP, Hadoop, MATLAB, Visual
		Studio, TFS, Eclipse, IntellijIdea, Net beans, Resharper,
		TortoiseSVN, Emacs, Latex
•	SDLC:	Waterfall, Agile Scrum
•	Platforms:	Linux, Windows, Unix

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

**Graduate Teaching / Research Assistant**, The University of Tennessee, TN

8/2014 - 2017

- Graded assignments and projects, and tutored for undergraduate classes 'Algorithm Analysis and Automata' and 'Software Engineering' for academic year 2014 - 2015
- Developed programs for simulations of mathematical models and plotting graphs using C/C++ and gnuplot for Dr. Sergey Gavrilets in Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Department for academic year 2014 – 2017
- Used cluster computing for simulations and fixed maintenance issues in the cluster

- Analyzed requirement and estimated time frame working with team and clients
- Developed applications in both Windows platform and Linux platform
- Followed **OOP** paradigm and **agile** scrum methodology in application development
- Developed web applications for health care system management in US using ASP.Net, ASP.Net
   MVC and C# as a member of outsourcing service provider team
- Designed and developed database schema and stored procedures in MSSQL and used LINQ queries with ASP.net MVC
- Developed and maintained US health care system management web application modules using **Grails** framework as a member of Deerwalk's product's team
- Designed and developed database schema, scripts and stored procedures in MYSQL
- Led developer's team for development and optimization of generic MYSQL scripts for importing staged data from multiple clients into company's product's database system
- Applied **Javascript**, **Jquery**, **Ajax** in client side scripting
- Generated reports using ItextSharp in .Net framework, and using Jasper and Rendering plug-ins in Grails
- Incorporated unit testing in .Net framework using NUnit, and in Grails using JUnit and Spock
- Employed **Web services** and **WCF services** with .Net application and **REST** service with Grails application

### **PROJECTS**

- Thesis on 'Efficient Simulation Of A Simple Evolutionary System' where we provide efficient computing methods for genetic algorithm using diploid population model and use it to analyze different behavior of genetic algorithm through simulations.
- Designed and developed mini shell system using **C** as part of requirement of graduate class
- Designed and developed program for simulation of different levels of cache and cache operations
- Used CUDA to develop Conway's Game of Life as part of GPU project for parallel computing
- Used OpenMP to develop parallel computing program and compare performance with serial computing program
- Developed Java programs to implement **Hadoop**'s MapReduce technique
- Implemented MPP, KNN, clustering, decision tree, neural networks using C++ and MATLAB in pattern recognition projects
- Designed and developed implementation of case study "The University Accommodation Office Case Study" in MYSQL
- Designed and developed radio frequency linked heart beat monitor and remote data logger as part
  of final project in undergraduate using photo transistor transceiver, micro-controller, RF
  transceiver and MATLAB